Let's talk about a simple approach on
how to think about building software
with coding agents. If you're just
starting, here's what usually happens.
You have an idea for an application or
software. You use a coding agent to
build it. It will probably create
hundreds of files, usually all at once
based on a very complex architecture.
And the result, most of the time it
fails. Then you learn about something
called specsdriven development. Now in
this case you provide your idea to the
same coding agent but the coding agent
is going to plan everything build up
features come up with specifications and
then it does its own research create
tasks for itself implements those tests
those and normally this approach works
relatively better. However in the
process as a new software developer or w
coder you don't really learn much. So
here is what I recommend
for new software developers or VIP
coders. This is what I'm calling VE
planning. And in here you should think
of the LLM or coding agent as a
collaborator or partner rather than a
software engineer that you just offload
tasks to. First you brainstorm your idea
with a coding agent. This coding agent
is going to be different than the one
that you going to use for final
implementation. But the most important
thing is that ask for feedback. Ask the
model to ask you clarifying questions.
That is extremely helpful especially for
your own learning. Use divide and
conquer. So rather than planning the
whole application, divide it into atomic
parts and plan those atomic parts. So
let's say if you have backend
integration with front end there are
certain APIs you want to divide in them
into different features or phases that
the coding agent will plan separately
while considering the big picture and
then you pick one feature at a time. You
plan that use another coding agent which
is separate from the planning agent to
implement that feature. You test it,
verify it using the initial coding agent
that created the plan and you iterate
this whole process. This will ensure
there are no regressions in performance
or it's not going to potentially touch
implementations that are already
working. You can follow this workflow in
almost any coding agent or you can use
specialized tools like tracer to help
you build this workflow without any
hassle. This lets you build plans for
each feature. Then use independent
agents like clot or co-pilot to do the
actual implementation
and let tracer verify the
implementation. In fact, it's just a VS
Code extension that you can install
inside your coding agent. I personally
really like their workflow and I'm
actually happy that they are making this
video possible through their
sponsorship. Now, the process I'm about
to show you is possible inside any
coding agent, but Tracer makes it a lot
more smooth and effortless. Now you will
need to install this extension in VS
Code or the choice of your own IDE and
then you need to sign up and can get
started with this for free. But let me
show you a practical example of how you
would use a workflow. Okay, here's the
tracer extension within VS Code. There
are two options. You can chat with the
AI to clarify the intent and then break
it down into manageable tasks. And the
second option is to create a detailed
file level plan, refine it with AI and
then send it to the agent for execution.
So what I'm going to do is we're going
to start with the phases. I want to have
a conversation with the agent to help me
build a plan and that's what I usually
do. So for example, I want to create a
web app that is going to be using HTML
for the front end. For the back end, I
want to use Google's nano banana
image model to generate images based on
the user prompt. The user will provide a
text prompt. The web app is supposed to
generate
four images. The user should be able to
select one of them. Then subsequently
pass this new image along with a text
prompt to keep generating. I want to use
the rest API. So I don't want to use any
SDK. Look up the documentation for nano
banana Google model with REST API. Okay.
By the way, this was realtime
transcription. I'm working on a
transcription app which is extremely
fast. So, we're going to send this in
and let's have a conversation with the
agent to come up with a plan. Right now,
it's actually doing Google search to
look for
Google's nano banana API endpoint. And
this is one of the best features I like
within Tracer. Unlike some of the other
agentic systems, it has the ability to
do web search and it decides to use that
tool whenever it's planning. Okay, so it
found Gemini 2.5 flash image which is
nicknamed nano banana. Then it asks us
about the API key. It's going to use
NodeJS.
It's making recommendations. It says you
mentioned HTML for the front end but
what backend technology we would like to
use. So options are NodeJS, Python. I am
comfortable with Python. So we're going
to say Python and then image generation
count. So this is going to be four
variation in one API call or make four
separate calls. So let's clarify these
for back end use Python and for
generation of multiple images use the
candidate count if that works. And for
storage, we can store it temporarily in
the memory. Okay, we're going to send
this in. Okay, so it came up with a
detailed plan. If you click on it, you
can see that it has multiple different
phases. So we can generate plan for each
of the phases. It completed a detailed
plan with all the requirements. Now,
interestingly,
Tracer actually comes up with an
implementation plan and that
implementation plan is up to a single
file. So, here are the different files
that it suggests to create and what is
supposed to be in each of those files.
At the moment, the project is empty.
Now, if we are happy with this plan,
then you can either execute this within
uh copilot tracer or you can pass it on
to cloud code. So we're going to execute
this within cloud code once we agree on
the implementation plan. And here you
can actually see that tracer keeps track
of the things. So it says do you want to
verify what cloud code has done? We can
go to the verification step. And here
our tracer is able to verify the
implementation from cloud code. Okay.
Once the back end is implemented now we
can go to Gemini REST API client. Again
we can go step by step and implement
every phase.
In this phase it wants to implement a
few more Python files. It also is
showing us what exactly the REST API is
supposed to look like. What are going to
be the different parameters? What are
the expected output? So extremely
detailed and this is exactly what you
want to do. Now we're going to pass it
on to cloud code to execute this. And
after that, we're going to test the
backend functionality to ensure
everything is working. I tend to do
incremental testing. That way, you can
keep track of the progress the agent is
making and also you can test different
components. Now, in order to test the
API endpoints, we'll need to provide our
Gemini API key. And it also added a link
to Google AI Studio, which is pretty
neat. Okay, so here it seems like it
found an issue with the implementation.
We're going to fix everything. So it
provides a context of what exactly the
fix needs to be. Once that feature was
implemented, I asked cloth to run a test
to see whether the API endpoint works or
not. It also found out a small bug, but
seems like everything is working at the
moment, right? So this is great. Now we
can build on top of this. So we're going
to go to the next stage. So it completed
another plan for the next step. We're
going to execute everything in cloud
code. Again, it opens yet another
terminal. But in every case, it provides
cloud code with enough context that it
actually knows what project it's working
on. Okay, so we just ran the final step.
Seems like it didn't find any
regressions, which is pretty great,
right? And as you can see, we're simply
building up one step at a time. and
tracer helps us keep everything in
check. Now the moment of truth. So there
were a couple of issues. For example,
that candidate count didn't work. So we
are now making four separate API calls
instead of using that. But let's run
this and let's see what the output we're
going to get. Okay. So here's what the
app looks like. Seems like there's a
text button or place to provide a
prompt. Then we can generate an image.
Also there is iterate with selected
image. So I think when it generates
images, we'll be able to iterate
hopefully. So let's see. Create an image
of a cat on a skateboard
on a beach.
There is uh sunset scene behind the cat.
Okay. So not the best of prompts, but
let's send this. Now it's going to be
making four different API calls and the
nano banana API calls do take some time.
So I'm going to come back when it
generates the images. Okay. So pretty
cool, right? So we have multiple
different images. Now you will also see
this text. Banana banana actually is a
multimodel model. So it generates images
along with text. Okay. So, all of them
look pretty cute, but I'm going to
select this one. And let's see if the
subsequent request is going to work. Put
a hat on the cat while it's drinking
orange juice on a sofa watching TV. All
right, so we're going to send this one
now and let's wait. Okay, so we get four
more cats. This cat definitely looks
very similar to the original one. So,
here's the one that we selected.
Although I think it did lose that scarf
over there. Uh but overall the
composition is very similar. So pretty
good job. And if you wanted to add
another feature, we could just add a new
face. We'll describe the phase and then
we can use tracer to help us implement
that. So overall, tracer is an extremely
powerful tool that can help you
do the planning for your five coding
applications. And I personally really
like this specsdriven development along
with verification that Tracer provides.
You can get started with Tracer for
absolutely free. You get 7day pro trial.
Link is going to be in the video
description. Now the goal of this video
was not only to show you a tool but
actually walk you through a complete
technique. And the goal is going to be
to break down your project into
manageable tasks. whether you are doing
w coding or development yourself and
then implement those task by planning at
it and you are going to provide a much
better context to your coding model.
Anyways, I hope you found this video
useful. Thanks for watching and as
always, see you in the next one.